[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
all right everyone welcome to the stoa
i'm peter limberg the steward of the
stoa and there still is a place for us
to cohere and dialogue about what
matters most at the nice edge of this
very moment
and today we are very lucky because we
have william mccaskill
uh william is an associate professor at
the university of oxford he's a
co-founder of the center for effective
altruism and the author of the book
doing good better and moral uncertainty
so effective altruism uh is a really
cool movement it's been around for a
while now
um i put in one of my memetic tribal
spreadsheets
uh and narayan will uh before i
introduce his will he'll
give a little bit more of what that is
and i'm sure we'll be talking about it
uh and we'll also kind of coined the the
anti-debate
uh term in one of his newsletters which
i ran with uh uh and which we're
experimenting with here with the
the stella so thank you will for for
putting that on my radar
um so i'm going to hand it to ryan who's
going to talk about the q a
protocols in a moment uh and narayan
he's a friend of the stoa
fellow trontonian and he's the founder
of something called think better which
actually came out
of the effect of altruism movement here
in toronto
so that being said i will allow everyone
to unmute themselves and i will take
narayan in
thanks peter i'm really excited to
facilitate today's session
we have 60 minutes today and
the format is going to be
i'll start off asking will a couple
questions and just sort of
feel out what is really alive with you
today will um
what's what's exciting for you and how
can you share
that with uh with this community um
i'm not sure how much you know about the
store or who these people are on this
call that are
uh going to sort of like listen to the
first part of this
um but we will invite everybody in to
participate so
for people here if you've got questions
feel free to pop those into the chat box
and we'll get to those once it feels
like
a good time
and feel free to also post if you would
like me to read your question for you
this is all being recorded for youtube
so if you don't want to be
on youtube also post that into the chat
and we can help with that so
i'm really excited just to ask a little
bit of
questions for will um well we've never
met before but i've been a member of
effective altruism
for the last three or four years um
hung out with the cea for a little bit
so i've definitely seen a whole bunch
of the waves that you've made in the
world um and very excited to
to speak with you um so i guess for the
group here
um if you don't mind sort of introducing
what
is effective altruism and who are you
what are
all of the other things that you do in
the world um
that are linked to and or outside of
effective altruism
sure yeah very happy to and thanks so
much for having me on
uh so effective altruism is about uh
trying to figure out how can we use our
time and money as effectively as
possible to make the world a better
place
and then once we've got some these
tentative answers to that question
taking action on that basis and so that
means
might mean doing research to figure out
what charity is most effective
that help other people or sentient
creatures by as much as possible with
the marginal dollar you can give them uh
and then you know first figuring out
what those most effective charities
and then uh taking action by donating to
them
or it might mean figuring out what are
the career paths where you can have the
biggest impact
and then after that pursuing those clear
um pursuing those career paths and
my role in this so way back in 2009
i co-founded giving what we can which
was an organization that encouraged
people to give at least 10
of their earnings uh to the most
effective charities
that of the charities they believed to
be most effective and we had a kind of
set of recommended charities there
and uh since then i've co-founded a few
other organizations
including 80 000 hours which focuses on
the career side of things providing
advice on
what um careers are most impactful
and what i'm working on most at the
moment is my research
at the global priorities institute which
is part of oxford
which is addressing some of the more
theoretical or fundamental questions
that you face
if you are an individual trying to have
the biggest possible positive impact on
the world
cool so hmm
a whole bunch of different directions
that we could go with this um
i imagine it would be pretty interesting
to talk a little bit more about some of
these global priorities that you're
looking at
what are some of the different ways that
individuals might choose to maximize
their impact
um yeah absolutely so um
additionally uh within effects of
altruism there's been
kind of four camps as it were
or at least tend to be four focus areas
so one which is kind of where i started
was focusing on global health and
development
the argument there being well if you
want to do the most good
focus on the poor very poorest people in
the world and we can certainly do an
enormous amount of good there
saving a life for just a few thousand
pounds uh a second
major cause area is uh
the welfare of animals on non-human uh
non-human animals
on factually farms where the sheer scale
of this problem is just
enormous you know 60 billion animals
killed every year for food
the vast majority of them are factually
found living in conditions of extreme
suffering
and in particular because this issue is
so neglected receiving just a few tens
of millions of dollars of
philanthropic funding every year there's
you can you know do an enormous amount
of impact
so significantly improving the lives of
hundreds of animals with every dollar
you spend
uh the third category are things that
are aimed at the long-term future
and making sure that civilization as a
whole
doesn't uh suffer some terrible
catastrophe
perhaps of its own making so climate
change i think obviously in this
category
um where uh
you know we are as a result of kind of
um economic growth without having the
technology to
reduce our carbon emissions uh we are
like
you know impaling the future of human
civilization if we were to continue in
this path for
um centuries to come uh this is the and
therefore making life worse for
generations centuries to come
but there are other things too that have
potential risks with
global catastrophe so i think there's
arguments for thinking that developments
in
synthetic biology in particular the
ability to make
new sorts of pathogens and developments
in artificial intelligence
are the sorts of technologies where we
want to be very careful and very
sensible
because things could go very well as a
result of those technologies or they
could go quite badly
and we want to be ahead of the curve and
proactive and
in particular these are some things
where the outcomes
could to the result could have effects
that last
centuries millennia or even like the
entire kind of future
of human civilization then the final
category are
what we call kind of meta activities so
things that
say well the most important thing
actually is
not any particular object level activity
but instead kind of building a movement
around these ideas getting more people
involved
or doing a research in order to figure
out uh what the most important
um what the most important things we can
be doing are
and those are the kind of four broad
categories of uh
things that people in effective
elections tend to focus on
and i think so 80 000 hours is an
organization that helps do a lot of
career coaching for
especially for people who are graduating
high school graduating university and
saying
the what it is that i want to do with my
life is to make the biggest impact in
the world
to do the most good that i can with my
life
and so as a community if effective
altruism is sort of looking in
these different categories of things uh
global health um animal welfare
long-term thinking and uh and meta
activities
how does how does one decide which of
these broad domains is even
the the most ethically correct or like
which which playground do i want to play
in for my life if i'm trying to make
this
decision yeah i mean it's a super tough
question and so that's the sort of thing
that
we're really focused on so one at least
set of heuristics that we like to use
when
comparing causes is what we call the
importance neglect and distractibility
framework
so here the idea is to think well
importance is just how big of a problem
is um
neglectedness is how many resources are
already going towards that problem
where in general it seems you can do
more good
on areas that are more neglected
relative to how
big a problem they are and then third is
factability which is just
how intrinsically difficult is this
problem how you know
how much um closeness can we make
with uh you know a given push
and when it you know most of the
kind of action when it comes to
prioritizing among these comes on how we
assess the importance side of things so
if i'm thinking about um you know animal
welfare versus the welfare of people
well you've got this incredibly tough
question about how you should weigh
the interest of humans against the
interests of non-human animals
uh when we're thinking about in issues
that might
impact the very long run we've got to
ask the ethical question of
um how should we weigh the interest of
future generations against the
um interests of the people today
how should we think about more
speculative impacts
where we're kind of less certain that
we are going to have any impact at all
but if we do it then it's going to be
very large
versus a greater guarantee of um
you know reliably having an impact that
you might be able to do in other areas
such as global health um and then
finally there's the question of
uh what moral philosophers call
population ethics
so some of these things like possibility
of man-made viruses
you know they threaten the survival of
the human race into the future
and that raises this question well how
bad would that be
uh in particular should we think about
like the loss of future lives
in the sense of them being prevented
from coming into existence
because the human race has gone extinct
before it's time
um how bad is that morally speaking and
there's been an enormous amount of kind
of philosophical debate there
and so i've talked about the kind of
mobile philosophy lens there are
obviously also um you know world view
judgments you have to make
like how likely do you think these
various
um risks of global could ask the vr um
how plausible do you think it is
the case for that we can do something
about them or similarly kind of
empirical questions on other areas too
um but uh once we start
getting into those um issues then you
can start getting a sense like okay how
big are these different problems
and then we can compare that against um
well how much funding
is already going towards them how much
um
uh and like how much does it look like
people are actually able to make
photographs in this area
yeah yeah and so we actually do have a
question from the audience so far so uh
for
for folks who have questions feel free
to pop those into the chat
um so this question is from dan um
he says how to address the critique that
capitalist
philanthropy is a form of misanthropy
and instead of addressing the
sociopathic and antisocial and
omnicidal behaviors at the core of a
single bottom line
political economy philanthropy just
addresses
the negative externalities of collective
epistemological and ontological
delusions
instead of rewilding politics and
building new worlds in new regenerative
economies
so that was a lot of words um my
understanding of this question
um is something akin to
uh thinking about particular issues um
issue by issue versus
looking at rebuilding a system or
totally changing the system
uh yeah so if again i thought um
the dan pog you know presumably had in
mind as well the thought that like
uh the root kind of problem here is um
you know kind of capitalist framework or
something and um
capitalist system and instead we should
be really trying to focus on
um creating alternatives to that
um so i think i guess a couple of things
um one is uh you know philanthropy can
be used to do
almost anything you know people um
associate philanthropy with kind of
giving arms um as in alms
not arms as in weapons um but you know
uh helping feed the sick and um
providing bed nets and so on
but you can also do it for you know
social and political experiments so
uh karl marx himself was funded by a
philanthropist um
uh frederick engels who was working at
his uncle's firm in order to provide
um for marx's writing and printing costs
um and similarly if you want as a
philanthropist then you can um
try and perhaps fund the search into
alternate
alter alternative um institutional
arrangements
um or expand living so
it's not in the nature of the philosophy
to debar yourself from doing that
um but then the second question is like
well is that the most effective thing to
do
um and there i suspect it's not um and
that's for
a couple of reasons um one is just the
feasibility of trying to
overthrow capitalism in favor of some
other um
institutional arrangement uh
historically other institutional
arrangements have not tended to work
very well
um i think we have a pretty good sense
of what the best countries
um ever have been and there's the kind
of scandinavian countries
denmark sweden where you have uh
private property ownership but large
amounts of redistribution
um and then secondly is just the fee but
then
you know i don't think that capitalism
is the end state of society i hope that
we move beyond it in the future
but then the second is just like well
the feasibility of doing so
where it seems that um to me that
being able to move off a capitalist
society in a new
in a way that seems robustly positive in
the near term
just seems kind of astronomically
unlikely to happen
and instead more targeted interventions
that
direct the kind of economic system we
have
in ways that we're avoiding like the
very worst outcomes
such as catastrophic climate change
which results from
implo uh inappropriately priced
um fossil fuel uh consumption
or um the uh
factory farming of you know billions of
animals that again results from like
inappropriate regulation
i think it makes more sense to target
those um
like very worst issues because then
you're going to be able to just like
move things somewhat but having enormous
benefits because you precisely because
you've targeted like
the very worst aspects of the problem
and and i think the other interesting
part about this is that
effective altruism as a community is
looking at a whole bunch of different
levels like i'm a part of a facebook
group which is effective altruism
systems change
um and it's people that are all talking
about how do we actually change the
rules in which the games are being
played
um and so it's interesting trying to
coordinate between a bunch of different
groups taking a bunch of different
strategies but it's almost as though the
portfolio of effective altruism
is going to be looking at the individual
cases as well as the system
uh yeah i think it's a great point is
that you know
we in effective autism very much see
this as a research project like an
ongoing
like it's like a methodology it's a
question that we're trying to address
and so it might be the case that you
have some
provisional set of answers um but
uh perhaps yeah different set of answers
a bit like
is better too and i've supported some
stuff that's trying to make um
institutional decision making better in
particular the center for election
science which is campaigning for
voting reform um in the u.s i've been a
champion of recently
and recommended the clan to them
um pranab would you like to read your
question
yeah sure thanks will one question i had
was
kind of surround philanthropy in general
and um one large competing philosophy
which you kind of hinted on
was that people often prefer to do
feel-good philanthropy
whether it's due to more like humanized
experience
or it's based on their own life
experience such as donational alma mater
or a cause that they personally feel
affected by
or stuff that just pulls at heartstrings
so i guess my question is what are your
views on that kind of motivation and
how do you think we could shift more
people maybe towards like a mix of that
plus effective altruism
um and then one question that robert
asked that was kind of a follow-up to
mine was
do you how do you kind of factor in the
effect on the giver
in um kind of marketing or maybe
working with effective altruism this
kind of i guess falls in the meta
activity increasing awareness
yeah yeah um yeah so again a great
question so i mean i think like
the motivation we have when we see
suffering in front of us and want to
take action
and um therefore like moved by that
um you know particular problem we've
seen perhaps it's like
you know an earthquake or a tsunami that
was in the news at a time
and um oh you want to help that
particular thing you know i just think
that's a really noble
instinct and i think for most of human
history that
following that instinct would have
served us fairly well
um and so it's just that we're in this
very odd circumstance where
our money and time can do so much good
often for perhaps people we will never
see or people we could never see those
people who will exist in the hundreds of
years to come
um that's like a very hard thing kind of
intuitively to get planned
and so that's why like what we try and
do is just um
firstly place those motivations and then
secondly provide arguments
and information to try and challenge
channel people
when they have that motivation to be
realizing okay i'm seeing this disaster
i'm really moved
but like this is just the problem that
is most salient to me now
um that's like i've seen a kind of
spotlight sean on this but there are so
many problems every day but i'm not even
not even thinking about most of the time
and i should just take this motivation
and use it to focus on where i can have
the biggest impact
um and so the way i feel about it is
just yet positive
but then wanting to channel it in the
right directions and i know that many
people
so for example who are giving what we
can members and pledge to do
10 of their income choose to
also on top of that give to some causes
that they just feel personally very
passionate about and i think that's
fantastic
um uh but the thing that i want to guard
against is people
um uh feeling like
oh well if i've just given to somewhere
that's kind of really moved me
i've therefore kind of done the most
good because i think that's that's
unlikely
um and then a follow-up question um
do i measure the effects upon the givers
um i mean we don't
so for example within giving what we can
uh
we don't have anything scientific um
on our members that are looking at kind
of how happy before or after
um i think it also wouldn't necessarily
generalize because we'd be looking at
those people who have opted into giving
ten percent
and it might be hard to do a randomized
controlled file of people giving ten
percent or not
uh we do have plenty of anecdote of
people
you know when you talk to a given what
we can member
they uniformly say there's been this
enormously rewarding and positive impact
on their life
um and that's in sync with the broader
psychological literature
which firstly uh
very strongly suggests that lower if
you're already in a rich currency lower
than your income by a bit such as by 10
makes almost a negligible difference to
your well-being
i certainly found that to be the case in
my life and then secondly there are
um personal benefits to giving as well
you feel good feel good about yourself
it's like humans are altruistic
creatures and
if you feel like you're helping to make
the world a better place well let's
speak a bit let's be a meaningful thing
um
and uh yeah that just seems to be borne
out by experience
most people i talk to don't really miss
the money but they do find it
a meaningful rewarding thing
so we've got a lot of really good
questions in here um
i think i want to continue playing into
just terms of like
the individual and their own personal
beliefs
and where they're going so i'm going to
pass things to uh david swedlow
if you want to ask your question yeah
thanks
um so yeah my question is it's
interesting that you mentioned it's the
individual because it's
there's a also it's an aspect of the
collective that's there which is um is
it helpful
for each person to stretch their
own personal um or collective
epistemological
development by feeling into the tension
between for instance
effectiveness and efficiency or between
the
enumerated categories that you listed
above
these these these tensions actually give
some personal
directiveness to what's important to me
and how do i
find that rather than looking at some
global oh this is the best thing or the
most efficient thing or the best good
that's done but
the tension of that feels like a a good
developmental frame and i'm curious
about your thoughts on that
uh okay so are you asking the question
of
how important is the fact that
yeah you might be personally very
delivered or motivated
towards certain causes um how should
that factor into the
question so to clarify you know the last
thing i ask there is
this implicates looking more deeply at
the motivation that might actually be a
selfless expression of wanting to
alleviate pain to alleviate alleviate my
own suffering
there's something that you you mentioned
um kind of
the the desire to kind of alleviate
suffering but
suffering is actually a beneficial
driver for our own personal development
and and evolutionary growth so we don't
want to completely diminish that
and there's some sense of um if we get
to
we can get kind of blindsided in an
altruistic movement
to trying to reduce suffering overall
rather than actually
finding the the most optimal
edge of suffering in our own personal
development and that's kind of what i'm
looking at is
is are there way do you have to see ways
of of actually
asking that question more personally how
do i how do i stretch into my own
suffering at the optimal level for me to
develop
okay yeah it's a good question where um
you know i'm normally talking to people
who are
already uh very motivated and often
cautioning against people
you know going too hard because there's
a risk you can burn yourself out like
you don't want to
you don't want to stretch yourself or
like feel so guilty run yourself down
into the ground
you never do any good at all um but on
the other hand you're absolutely right
like
seeing something feeling pain in
response to that that's like an
appropriate
um reaction and in my own case like
when i first was thinking about these
ideas and i was trying to decide
how much of my income should i try and
give away over the course of my life
um i just went on
google for images um looking up images
of children suffering from neglected
topical diseases
and just kind of just clicked through
just these horrible images time after
time
and that was just very motivating for me
because i just thought well
um you know there was one child who's
had um elephantiasis um of the face it's
just
um clearly just like a debilitating
condition
and i just thought well if my money
could just prevent
one child like um so if there's money i
could give could just prevent one child
from suffering from a condition that you
know that extreme
um wow that would be just completely
worth it but i can actually do that like
hundreds thousands of times
um over and so i think there is an
optimal balance
um i think that can be a reason for
visiting developing countries if you're
interested in global health and
development
visiting factory farms um uh
in order to get kind of upfront
uh evidence um about what this
suffering is like uh but on the other
hand you don't want to go too far
and certainly by the time
that you know i think of this like pain
like guilt turmoil is like the thing
that can like really
get you off your seat and then doing
something and then
once you find you know you've decided
what percentage of your income you want
to give
perhaps you have now moved your career
onto a path where you think it could be
high impact
at that point i encourage kind of
thinking about it like a job like kind
of like anything else
because if you're just like trying to
you know get more juice out of yourself
by really beating yourself up day out
day
day after day that's not sustainable um
whereas
if you pick kind of light levels that
you think yes i would be happy with this
level of effort for the rest of my life
like that's where you want to be i think
one of the groups that i imagine is sort
of placing a bunch of tension
into the collective consciousness uh and
i don't know if suffering would be the
right
term would be um extinction rebellion um
really forcing humanity to look
straight at um the climate change
problem
um peter you've got a question that sort
of relates in that area
yeah so i'll read my question i have two
questions but i'll say this one first so
uh before
kovid i was planning on setting up a
dialogue actually with uh
ea ryan's group here in toronto with the
local extinction rebellion group
and there are other groups like
extinction rebellion that are trying to
address
existential risks suffering risks the
meta crisis
but are doing so with uh wildly
different methods
do you have any thoughts on these groups
um xr or otherwise
uh do you think there are other ways to
do good uh or do you sense that the ea
is the right approach that should be
wildly uh widely adopted
uh terrific yeah so um i feel
yeah very positive on extinction
rebellion
um seems like uh certainly in the uk
where um i know about
more um just managed to really
um get this incredible upswell
of protests and involvement from a very
large number of people
very quickly um in response to one of
the most important problems of our time
um and you know that's just fantastic
and policy and politicians just like do
take this seriously
um it would be
something i'd like to see more of is
like a focus on
particular um solutions
so uh i think politicians really can
bend
um to popular pressure like this and you
want to make it as
like easy and direct for them to do that
as possible
in particular by saying like what we
want to see is this particular thing
my own view and the most effective
the most effective actions that any
individual country
or philanthropist but let's focus on
currency can do in response to
climate change um is funding
uh innovation in clean energy and
the reason for that is uh take a country
like
um the united kingdom it's responsible
for about four percent of global
emissions
so if the united kingdom gets all the
way down to zero emissions um
itself uh that's done a very limited
amount
to um reduce climate change and in fact
other countries might compensate to some
extent
um in contrast if it spent a similar
amount as it spends on
aid for example on clean energy
innovation it would double the clean
energy innovation budget
and that is a benefit that was spread
all over the world because if you can
make it cheaper
um to get energy from uh clean sources
rather than fossil fuels um then
uh just see what the power of um
self-interest although um other
countries will
uh follow suit um
and so i think that's fairly powerful
and i think that like the protest
movements
um could be considerably more powerful
again if they had a kind of
message like that that was saying like
look we've consulted with like oil and
policy experts and we think
like this exact thing is what you should
be doing
um especially if that message is like
partly designed to be something that um
you think
that the government kind of really could
um could get on board with
uh and then you had another question
about criticisms but um i'll pause for
the moment there
yeah uh i'll ask that one um let me just
read it
okay so are there any criticisms of the
effective altruism movement
uh an approach that you have encountered
if so could you
share to believe steel man them yeah so
i mean i think
uh the best criticisms
of um effective altruism
are about the particular focuses that
we've
chosen rather than about the kind of
general approach
so my views that kind of general
approach
work out what does the most good and
then
take action on that basis seems pretty
hard to dispute with
um to dispute um whereas you could say
look there's gonna be errors along the
way
um or you've like made a mistake with
like the particular focus areas
and one line of criticism that we've
often had
is this quest from both directions
actually
is the issue of how much should you rely
on more easily quantifiable netflix
versus
on things that are just more speculative
like harder to quantify
and certainly in the early days of
effective altitude we focused
very hard on those metrics that are more
easily quantifiable at least like cost
per life saved or per year of
healthy life given or just simply
dollars transferred
into the bank accounts of the poorest
people in the world and people often
felt like that was kind of
focusing on the quantifiable at the
expense of the kind of bigger picture
now that we focus on
much much more on these issues that
impact the long term
like ensuring that developments of
developments in synthetic biology or ai
go well
we sometimes get criticism from the
other direction uh which is
well well do you even know these things
that are doing good like how on earth
would you measure progress in this area
and um i think that's a good criticism
too
so uh there just is this fundamental
trade-off
between pursuing what you can measure
what you can get reliable feedback loops
on
there you might kind of be more
confident you're going to do a bit of
good
versus trying to focus on the thing that
you just think is most important
in a global sense but then taking
actions that
uh where it's just much harder to know
if you're actually making progress
um and so in a sense i think the
criticisms on either side there just
like are reasonable in our strong and
that's something that hopefully
continued debate and research can ensure
we make
later progress on cool thank you
i think uh sahil's first question would
be a good follow-up for this one
okay oh sure
yeah hey uh and hi lions nice to see you
again
uh so well my question is uh about gpi
so can you talk about any particular
work of gpr you think has made some real
progress or at least looks highly
promising
uh yeah sure i'm happy to talk about
that so um
this uh i'll caveat is
you know not just gpi but it is um
you know continuing work that's occurred
over the last two decades
but is this field of population ethics
so
uh intuitively it
you would think that kind of ethics is
about making people happy but not making
happy people
so if i say well
consider kind of two futures um
and they only differ by the fact that in
one future
there's an additional person living a
kind of flourishing life
many people at least intuitively think
well you've got no reason to bring one
future about
rather than another um because um
there's no kind of moral requirement to
add an extra person to the world even if
that person is going to be very happy
and i think there's actually just very
robust arguments
uh for showing that that show that that
just can't be the
that can't be the case um
one such argument is just imagine a
third world where we've now got that
additional person
let's call him bob and we make it and
he'd be even happier
and okay that world is definitely better
than the world in which bob comes into
existence and is a bit less happy
but if you think that the third world is
better than the second world
then you can't think that they're both
equally as good as the first world
um so we at least can't understand the
idea of it being
neutral to add a person to the world um
in the sense of it
you know keeping the world equally good
and so in fact i think that um
there are good arguments for thinking
that at least when someone is
going to be have a sufficiently good
life perhaps like a very flourishing
life
then it just does make the world better
in partial sense
to um you know bring that person into
existence
and that becomes really crucial when um
we think about risks that could risks of
human extinction so
asteroids we're familiar with perhaps
worst case climate change
uh also like i was talking about risks
from synthetic biology
man-made viruses and so on because then
we're cutting off civilization and
after the point in time at which we go
extinct there's just
nothing in the future um but that would
be potentially like trillions upon
trillions of lives lost in the future
and if you do think that's a moral loss
because those people would have
or many of those people would have had
flourishing lives well
that means that um
that means that like plausibly avoiding
a risk of human extinction
or similar catastrophes that would
curtail
humanity's potential for desirable
development might be the most important
thing because the scale is just so large
there would be so many future people um
uh who you know whose absences um
would be lost whose lives would be lost
uh and so i think that's
um kind of one of the contributions that
gpi has made that is
quite different from common sense on the
matter but
uh is or you know by common sense i mean
are
kind of unphilosophical um intuitions on
the matter that i think is a
crucial importance when we're thinking
about the
most important problems in the world
i like that that we've gone everywhere
from
specific recommendations on climate
change to
moral philosophy and i think that that's
one of the things that's so special
about effective altruism
is the connection within one community
from
the deep moral questions that will flip
you from
one cause area to another um
and connecting that all the way to
actual work on the ground where
there are people there measuring results
in terms of live saved donation
money um sent and i think it's just so
cool because
when sahil asked that question i wasn't
sure whether the answer was going to be
something a little bit more like
we helped shaped the thinking of
the effect of altruism movement and of
course waves out into the world of other
people trying to do good
or if it was going to be something a
little bit more concrete
uh yeah thanks i hadn't hadn't really
thought before about
the fact that effective autism is so
unusual in having such a breadth from
like the fundamentals all the way to the
practice
but certainly when it comes to doing
research it's
i find it very helpful to be engaged
with the kind of coal face
what are the things that most important
to be doing
and that helps me prioritize within this
my research because i can then
have a much better sense of like what
are the questions that are most
important to be answering
in order for us actually to be making
progress at making the world better
and uh i think that's quite unusual
within philosophy where
the normal pathway is much more like
getting taken by some intellectual
puzzle or something even
uh if it's not maybe the most practical
of things
so i'm going to invite uh auslan bishop
to read
their question
i was just wondering about the
different methodologies that you may
have used to look at the
quantitative and qualitative approach
while studying this and also if
there's been efforts or if you've just
perhaps created and found places that
the inventories of all the risks and
possibilities and effectiveness and the
aspects that you mentioned in terms of
importance i think the
ability and you know neglectedness
and so forth uh is there a repository
along those lines and
also i was wondering uh
who else might be collaborating and just
thinking that uh
un's initiatives and sustainability
related goals and so is do you
are you aware of some global
coordination systematic
and especially quantitative wise
uh yeah so it's a great question uh the
best resource
that i would recommend for everyone is
toby awards the precipice
um it's a book by a releasing colleague
um
and so in terms of cat you know
uh creating a kind of ranking of global
catastrophic risks
uh it's doing this quantitatively
is much easier at least for
natural risks such as from asteroid
impacts
or super volcanoes which are very large
volcanoes that have been implicated in
previous mass extinctions
uh all kind of natural pathogens as well
and you know quantitatively we can
assess that the risks there are very low
so perhaps on the order of you know one
in um i get like yeah you know one in a
hundred thousand or one in a million
over the course of a century
um so still be great if they were zero
but um still very low
where it gets harder to make a
quantitative estimate is uh
on natural or man-made
risks so the risks that we face such as
from
uh like novel viruses because there we
don't have a track record
so we're just having to make you know
make guesses make informed expert
opinion
and uh at least when it comes so the
other area that we focus on a lot is
artificial intelligence
where there's a worthy that that could
be a point of
lock-in of a particular set of values at
a time once you develop
advanced artificial intelligence perhaps
technological progress goes very quickly
and whoever controls that is then able
to just shape the entire future
and there you can start you know
there is work to just try and get better
estimates better understandings
such as surveys among experts of when we
should expect to have
artificial intelligence that's at human
level or greater
in terms of its abilities uh where the
typical prediction is saying well it's
something like
uh 40 years um 40 years time
uh from if you look if you ask experts
this question
um
and then you can also um look at other
things like
you know how much what are the trends
and computational power
at what point will we have sufficient
amounts of computing power that we could
just
basically simulate a human brain where
current ai models
um have about the computational power of
a honeybee
but that's still not giving you kind of
quantitative estimate of the magnitude
of the risk of the cup
of the coming century so there's going
to be a judgment call
toby has a table in his book where he
gives his own personal estimates of
the size of existential different
existential risks
so he thinks there's a ten percent
existential risk from ai in the coming
century
a three percent um risk from uh man-made
viruses
and those are the kind of bulk of the
probability um but he's very very keen
to stress that these are just subjective
estimates it's
bet it's you know helpful for people in
order to understand his views
that he's giving such estimates but uh
it's not that you can
claim that it's not like saying the
probability of flipping a coin and
getting a heads is 50
where uh you have some notion of
frequency by which you can make sense of
the probability
uh and then in terms of um collaboration
with the un
uh not yet hopefully one day
um if these ideas are gaining more
attraction gaining more attention then
um
yeah something i would love to see is uh
a u.n department that is or organization
that is explicitly focused on
long-term risks um and the sorts of
events that could
uh impart all the future of civilization
thank you thank you
i think for me like after after reading
the
i posted a book review of the precipice
from uh slate star codex which i think
is pretty good and it actually has that
table there
um that's where toby ord basically says
there's
his rough estimate is like a one in six
chance that humanity doesn't survive the
next
century which like
to be on a stowa call and hear that
somebody
is making this prediction and then if
you do research you realize
wow this guy's actually put a lot of
work into this there's a whole bunch of
people that are actually believing this
and like
what does that do to you internally in
terms of setting your own life
priorities like
i know the old version of me would hear
that and it would just sort of like roll
off my back but that's like one of the
most
heavy things to think about um
yeah so i'm i'm curious if anything's
going to come out of just sort of like
that if that drives any curiosity for
people on this
on this call um so we do have about 10
minutes left i've got it so if you have
any remaining questions um
feel free to pop them in uh david
i saw that your question got a whole
bunch of plus ones so
um if you'd like to read that one next
yeah thanks um
you know i was thinking a little bit
more about the question i asked before
and i said feeling into it a bit more
um my my driver my thing behind the the
motivation behind it is that
i have a keen interest in human beings
developing a better sense of
unintended consequences that seems to be
something we're really bad at
and i'm wondering if there are better
ways that we can use collective feedback
loops
um to explore potential fitness
landscape hill climbing
um looking at strange attractors and
really looking at that like
the near-term hills seem to be the ones
that are most attractive and i would
like to expand it ai seems to be
something that can move in that
direction there are other things but you
know john verveiki also
points at looking at relevance
realization and four ways of knowing as
a way of developing wisdom to
to to broaden the perspective
so um i recognize that my motivation is
mostly kind of a meta motivation it's
not so much specifically how
you would do this but it's like how can
we apply
this in a more and a more um broad
broadway does that make sense uh yeah
that makes sense and
um yeah i mean i think that one of the
you know there's a very promising focus
area
uh which is kind of improving
decision making or you're just improving
society in ways
such that it's more likely to be
optimized for
um you know what's best in the long run
even though you haven't made any like
deliberate focus on any one particular
issue but you've swept your things such
that
society will make better decisions and
so i'll highlight um
two two things that i think are um
particularly promising there
uh one is uh philip tetlock's work on
forecasting which we've funded quite a
bit of
um where what he has shown
is that at least for some people by
making decisive probability judgments to
estimate
um the size of uh
if you get people to make precise
probability judgments to estimate
um the likelihood or not of various
geopolitical events
some people at least are very good at
doing this um
and are much better than experts um
uh who are like not similarly trained um
at making such predictions
and this is very different from how
normal political decision making works
which is like it's both very vague it's
all very qualitative
people aren't making kind of precise
predictions and certainly not relying on
what are called super forecasters people
who are very good at making such
predictions
and so one thing we've been trying to
push on and would like to see more of
is this just getting built into
government much more um
so that governments are now making
decisions that
uh more accurately reflect
reality like reasonable probabilities
assigned
to different year political events
uh the second is then on
you know what governments is what
governments you get given a certain set
of voter preferences
where the voting reform that i've
championed is
trying to move us from first past the
post voting
where just you go and you just vote for
a single candidate to approval voting
where
you vote for as many candidates as you
can and
uh oh good i'm glad you're the fan and
that has just is a tiny change to the
voting system but has
mathematically far better properties
where it means you avoid vote splitting
where perhaps you've got you know two
democrats and one republican and
each democrat gets 30 and the republican
gets 40
and then wins um that's like a bad
outcome should be
even though most people would prefer
either of the democrats to win a
republican
so um vote splitting is a way in which
people
aren't really getting what they want
from this voting system um and when
surveys have been done it's just like
better
representing the will of the people uh
and so that's a way in which we would
end like if this were widely adopted and
it's had satisfaction
um then the governments that would be
elected
are those that would better reflect the
will of the people and uh that would
seem like a very
good thing
thank you and let's go to pranab
with his question hey again
um yeah the i guess the question i had
is
really around the fourth focus area i
think i find myself being drawn to it
um what are some interesting learnings
in how the ea movement has grown over
time
in this focus area and what kind of
initiatives or approaches have you seen
emerge that you didn't quite expect
in getting more people involved in this
uh yes i think the the biggest thing
is just being surprised at how many
people
have taken very serious amounts of
giving seriously
so um when i first
uh yeah when i was first thinking about
setting up giving what we can
uh lots of people were saying this is
crazy 10 is way too high
um and we just kind of wanted to stick
to our guns on that
um and i really think we were vindicated
there and in particular
there's this kind of correlation between
how much people are willing to give
and how effectively they're willing to
give it um
and then like whether they're also
willing to go out and do other things
like change their career and so on
and so that means that like these people
the
proportion of people who are just really
most committed take these really
seriously trying to do the most good
just have a really outsized impact
because perhaps they're
giving ten times as much as they would
have done and a hundred times more
effectively
you know they're having a thousand times
the impact that they would otherwise
have had
um and so yeah that's pretty interesting
and then
the fact that such people are just so
receptive to rational arguments
um has also been a big kind of piece of
learning for me where
uh if you look at the psychology
literature
it uh suggests that what you want to do
is have kind of
smiling children and they have these
kind of uh or like a single individual
whose story you tell
that's the way to get people to give but
those studies have actually just done on
very small amounts of money something
like 20 cents or 50 cents
because otherwise it'd be very expensive
for
the searchers and i think the way people
think about very large amount
commitments
um such as 10 of income it's just
extremely different from
how you would make this kind of quick
decision when you're you know
asked like oh hey do you want to give
five dollars to this thing
and i think for such a large decision
people are much more likely to engage
their
kind of analytical brains and really
kind of think through a decision
uh then the final thing i'll say about
um things i've learned over time it's
just the power and importance of
community
where we didn't set out
to kind of build an effective community
really and it was just
interesting to see how rapidly and
organically that grew
and now being part of it i can see it
really makes sense where
you know it's tough to perhaps be
acting in ways that are somewhat more
unconventional but such as by giving
significant proportion of your income or
making clear changes and it can be scary
too
especially when you're doing things for
people you will never meet or
these causes that seem kind of abstract
um
but having a community of people that
share your values well that's really
rewarding that's really motivating
and i think that helps very
significantly with people kind of
sticking it out longer term
thank you thanks will
i'm thinking so just as we're wrapping
up i'm thinking about
the stoa as its own emerging community
right now and i
know there's a lot of people on here
that are hoping to change the world in a
variety of different ways um so i guess
when i passed things over to peter peter
i'm wondering if you'd actually
answer a little bit about like how
how are you seeing the stoa community um
and realizing that
at least from my perspective i think
that there is some influence from the
effect of altruism community in some of
the discussions that have happened here
um i'm just wondering if you'd like to
touch on that briefly
and then and then maybe uh make your
final announcements and and will thank
you so much for
all of this this was fantastic yeah
thank you still the enjoyable discussion
yeah i'm trying to figure out the most
strategic way to hop skip
around that question i don't want to
answer it right now
but i will say that i do take
inspiration from will
and the ea movement and what they've
done and sort of stole as like an
incubator inviting all these different
what i call medic tribes in to kind of
have idea sex
uh really and to figure things out and
um
and sometimes your blind spots or your
cognitive biases get exposed by getting
revealed to a radically different
philosophy than your own
and that's kind of like the space that
the store is evolving into
um so that being said uh thank you
narayan for excellent emceeing and
putting me on the spot there
and thank you will for coming uh to the
stoa uh it's greatly appreciated we'd
love to have you back
thank you and before i close out
officially let's make a few brief
announcements um for upcoming events
we've got daniel schmochtenberger uh
coming in
at 7 30 pm eastern time for the digital
porch he's
our sense maker in residence so this is
his third out of
four uh parts um
that's how it's going to be really
exciting and then tomorrow we have
33 myths of the system uh darren allen
he's a
kind of this like edgy anarchist and
i'll read the blurb of that event
a civilization reaches end game and
begins to disintegrate uh
as the illusions of left and right
coalesce to a single spectacular omni
myth
as every rootless mind begins to
directionally experience the stupefying
dystopias
the time has come to understand the
whole system from root to fruit
so yeah a little bit something different
to have some more idea sex here at the
stoa
so that being said uh you can check out
our website to rsvp to those events
uh we have a patreon and a newsletter
sub stack
all right everyone thanks so much for
coming to stowa